Inventory of the Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah [Iraq Memory Foundation] records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Appendix: List of Iraqi Testimonies Interviewees with English subtitles, 2007-2008
  - Mehdi Kassem Lafteh Temimy, 2007 April 11; 11.14 minutes
    "Born in Basra in 1963, during primary school, he was forced to join the Ba'th party. He was arrested in 1979 and was violently beaten and accused of writing slogans opposing the government. He was forced by torture to falsely admit that he wrote those slogans. After months of detention and torture he was referred to the Revolution Court where he was sentenced to imprisonment in the school for delinquents where he spent a year and a half, and then he was transferred to the special judgment department of Abu Ghraib Prison where he had to spend four years more. This testimony was given in Basra on 11-04-2007."
  - Nehme Omran Abbas Ardawi, 2007 May 3; 12.01 minutes
    "He was born in Hendie in 1948; he finished his complementary studies and enrolled in the army. He was harassed during the military service because he did not belong to the Ba'th party. He was injured in one of the battles so he was discharged and took many jobs here and there. He was arrested in 1980 for belonging to the Da'wah Party; he was violently beaten, electrocuted, mocked and humiliated. He was imprisoned for 8 months in a small solitary cell. They wrote a deposition for him and he was taken to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to 10 years of prison. This testimony was given in Karbala on 3-05-07."
  - Said Mohssen Hamd Yassery, 2007 April 13; 7.85 minutes
    "He was born in Nehmanie in 1959 in a peasant family from an aristocratic background. He received a diploma in commerce in 1979. He was forced to join the Ba'ath party against his will so he distributed publications opposing the party in the mid-eighties. He was in the military but chose to flee the army fearing for his life. He hid for a while in many places and some of his relatives got arrested, among them his uncle who was sentenced to death. Security forces raided his home and arrested everybody inside even the women and children, and because he was not arrested his brothers were arrested and executed. This testimony was filmed in Wasset on 13-04-2007."
  - Jawher Hama Law, 2006 December 6; 7.20 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Jahwar Hama Law is from Selmaniah, a physics teacher he witnessed the collective arrests and shelling of the villages of Selmaniah. In 1987 as he was coming home from a visit to his brother in one village he got arrested and was sent to the emergency department of Selmaniah and accused of cooperating with the guerillas because he was traveling on a road leading to one of the security prohibited villages. He was released after 8 months of detention. He lost his academic year. In 1989, he was arrested again and he was a student he was detained for three months in the general security department in Baghdad without knowing what he was accused of. This testimony was given in Selmaniah on 6-12-2006."
  - Furat Saleh Abd Hussein, 2007 January 20; 14.50 minutes
    "From Bassra, a writer and an author, he got a diploma in business administration and economy from Bassra University. He received awards in story writing. In the beginning of the 90s, he formed with some of his colleagues a special literary forum. In 1992, security forces raided the forum and arrested all the authors and accused them of engaging in political activities. He moved between many prisons and penitentiaries and for long months he and his colleagues endured various kinds of torture and insult. They were freed after a long suffering that lasted a whole year. This testimony was filmed in Bassra on 20-01-2007."
  - Alaa Wasseem Aoude, 2007 April 6; 14.10 minutes
    "He was born in Bassra in 1965 he graduated from the teacher's academy in Bassra in 1989. He was viciously harassed because he didn't belong to the Ba'th Party. During the presidential census of 1995 he was accused of not voting. Some days later he was arrested in the security station of Bassra and was subjected to terrible torture. After one year of suffering he was transferred to the general security department of Baghdad then he was moved to the special security court where he was sentenced to death then the sentence was reduced to 15 years. He spent 6 years in the prison of special sentences in Abu Ghraib then he got released. This testimony was given in Bassra the 6-04-2007."
  - Kawthar Shatb Rabie, 2007 March 19; 8.41 minutes
    "Born in 1955 in Kasseem from a communist family. She studied economy in the USSR. In 1979, the raids on the communist party began so her husband hid in a small shelter for two years then he was discovered and killed. Kawthar was arrested in 1980. She was humiliated and photographed nude. She had a miscarriage during torture. After two years in prison she was sentenced to seven years in jail. She was discharged because of a general amnesty still she was repeatedly arrested and tortured where the traces of burning are still obvious on her body. This testimony was given in Hella on the 19-03-2007."
  - Hassan Ali Atabi, 2007 February 17; 10.46 minutes
    "He was born in Shatra in 1926. A journalist from a communist family. In 1973, he worked with Kurdish organizations and the Ba'th party after the announcement of the front but they were under surveillance from their partner in the front, the Ba'th party. His daughter Amal and his son Safaa were not accepted in the Teachers' League because they did not belong to the Ba'th party and his son Samy was an artist who was constantly hassled because he refused to join the Ba'th Party. In 1981, Samy was arrested and in the middle of 1984, Hassan was informed that his son was executed. He sustained with his sons many harassments after the execution of his son Samy. Because of the bad security situation the team had to cut the filming of the testimony and get back to it later. This testimony was given in Baghdad on 17-02-2007."
  - Murtada Abd Kareem Hussein, 2007 April 9; 13.10 minutes
    "He was born in Bassra in 1972. In 1991, he treated some wounded men for the guerillas and some soldiers and he nearly died because of it. In 1999, a large group of policemen raided his house to arrest his brother who was charged with participating in a demonstration against the government after the assassination of the religious man Mohammad Sadek Sadr. Some days later Murtada got arrested instead of his brother and he was beaten then released. A few months later he was arrested again and was cruelly tortured without being accused of anything, he stayed one year in prison then he was sentenced to another year in jail without being charged. This testimony was filmed in Bassra on 9-04-2007."
  - Jassem Mohammad Alawi, 2008 June 6; 6.42 minutes
    "From the city of Al-Neseriah, he works as a guard. He was arrested and charged with being a member of the Da'wah Party. He was severely beaten especially on the head, which led to paralysis in his hands and a permanent tremor in his whole body. He was referred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to life in prison. When the people's uprising took place in 1991, he and a number of other prisoners were beaten with bludgeons on the head. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Naseriah on 6/6/2008."
  - Ayeshaa Fakhry Abdallah, 2008 March 13; 8.06 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in 1920, in the village of Swaga Kon, part of the Sulaymaniyah District, she now resides in the city of Al Sulaymaniyah in the town of Pera Macron... She lost two of her sons, Aziz and Abbas, when they were arrested and charged with assisting the Peshmerga forces. Their family house was plundered and burned by the government forces after the arrest of her children... Till today she does not know their whereabouts but she hopes they are still alive. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al Sulaymaniyah on 13/3/2008."
  - Hammed Suhail Najem Abu Ousaibeh, 2008 December 12; 7.52 minutes
    "From the city of Najaf, he works with his parents as mortuaries in the Graveyard of Najaf. During the uprising of 1991 he was serving in the military, and when he returned he found out that his family had been stranded and his father shot dead by a sniper. He was stranded along with his family for many days and their properties were seized even though none of them took part in the uprising. A month later his younger brother Mohammad Rida was arrested and till this day he is still missing. This testimony was recorded in the city of Najaf on 12/12/2008."
  - Amal Abd El-Amir Abd El-Raheem, 2008 June 15; 9.09 minutes
    "Born in 1949, in the city of Al-Samawa. Her family suffered a great tragedy when 7 of her brothers were executed. Her brother Hussein was arrested when he fled from the military service and was immediately sentenced to death. Months later she was asked to go and receive the dead body of her captured brother Mohammad; he was executed for being a member of the Da'wah Party. As for the other five their fates are still unknown. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Samawa on 15/6/2008."
  - Akram Jaafar Saadallah Tozlo, 2008 March 15; 12.27 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in 1933, of Turkmen origin, 'Toz Khormato' District, a part of Tekreet Province. A well known artist, he was persecuted and captured many times due to his poems and songs. He refused to sing for Saddam Hussein so he was threatened by the authorities. He was last captured in 1986 and was sentenced to life imprisonment. After being sent to prison, his wife and children were captured and banished to the prison of Nakrat El Sulman in Al-Samawa desert. This testimony was recorded in the city of Karkook on 15/03/2008."
  - Aras Abed Akram, 2008 June 6; 10.32 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in 1966, and resides in the city of Halbaja. In 1986, and while the city was being bombarded by chemical weapons, Aras was one of those whose families were completely annihilated from the attacks where he lost 14 members of his family including his father, mother,7 sisters and 3 brothers in addition to losing a great number of relatives as they were all exterminated. Men, women and children. This testimony was recorded in the city of Salimanieh on 6/6/2008."
  - Ayad Jari Tahram, 2007 September 29; 10.00 minutes
    "From a family of farmers from The City of Basra. During the Iraq-Iran war, their pastures in the Shat El Arab district were sheared and planted with field mines of which today they still suffer. He was arrested in 1984 with the charge of belonging to the Da'wah Party and he was moved around several camps. He was severely tortured with beating and electrocution, and his shoulder was permanently dislodged and he still suffers from it today. He was transferred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to life in prison. This testimony was recorded in the city of Basra on 29/9/2007."
  - Abd Al Bawi Kadr Mohammad, 2008 March 13; 10.35 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "From the area of Surdash, a division of the City of Al Sulaymaniyah, he was arrested in 1985 and tortured; charged with being involved in political activities and sympathizing with the Peshmerga forces. After a few days his older brother Abd El Jabbar was arrested as well... he and his brother endured the cruelest forms of torture with beating and electrocution. They were referred to the Revolution Court where Abd Al Bakqi was sentenced to 15 years in jail, and his brother was sentenced to life imprisonment. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al Sulaymaniyah on 13/3/2008."
  - Zuhair Abdul Hussein Jassem, 2008 February 18; 9.23 minutes
    "From the City of Baghdad, he was arrested in 1980 from his unit and charged with belonging to the Da'wah Party. He was moved around a number of military and civilian camps and subjected to severe torture, he was forced to sign a false statement, and then he was transferred to the Revolution Court and sentenced to death and then the sentence was reduced to life imprisonment. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Kadhimiya on 18/2/2008."
  - Abd Kareem Hassan, 2008 August 5; 7.15 minutes
    "Born in 1923 in the city of Al-Samawa. After the uprising in 1991, 3 of his sons were arrested, even though they didn't take part in the events. He went through a lot to get news of his children... In the first months of their arrest, he was able to see them and they showed signs of severe torture. Later, he was forbidden to meet with them and didn't hear any news of them until their bodies were discovered in a mass grave in 2003. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Samawa on 5/8/2008."
  - Karim Murih Abd Basha Al-Oueidi, 2007 December 20; 12.37 minutes
    "From the city of Qassem, a teacher, he was arrested in 1982 without any known cause. He was transferred between many prisons and camps and endured all types of torture without even knowing why. He witnessed the death of a number of detainees. He was referred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to 5 years in prison, which he spent in Abu Ghraib. This testimony was recorded in the city of Qassem on 20/12/2007."
  - Tohfa Shalaka Touaiher, 2008 April 5; 8.43 minutes
    "Born in 1936 in the city of Al-Samawa, her son Kazem was a student in the University of Architecture. He was persecuted and wanted as he was accused of being a member of the Communist Party. Kazem had to go to Kurdistan and work there. There, he vanished and no one knew of him. It became later known that he had been arrested and executed and a strange woman had claimed his body and buried him. Her other son Wasfi, who was studying management and administration, was arrested a month later and executed as well. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Samawa on 5/4/2008."
  - Abdallah Mohammad Hussein, 2008 March 8; 9.54 minutes
    "Born in 1949 in the Sedar village, a part of the Al Sulaymaniyah district. In 1988 army units stormed his village and arrested a large number of the villagers and among those arrested was his family, which was composed of his wife and 8 children. He knew nothing of their fate until their remains were found in 2007 in one of the mass gravesites in the city of Al-Hadar in Mousel. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al Sulaymaniyah on 8/3/2008."
  - Hussein Faleh Saffah, 2008 April 6; 9.52 minutes
    "From the city of Al-Samawa, his father, who was a shepherd in the area of Kokrat Al-Salman, found a Kurdish boy, shot down; his name was Tymour. He took the boy in and mended his wounds. It turned out that the child was in a mass execution campaign that included his family, and he was able to climb his way out of the burying hole after he was shot. Hussein's family raised the boy and kept him safe until he was older, then they secretly sent him to Kurdistan to live with the remaining members of his family. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Samawa on 6/4/2008."
  - Afrouz Mustafa Amin, 2008 March 12; 9.34 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "From Al Sulaymaniyah city, she spent years living in fear and terror of the heavy bombardment of her city. Her brothers, Asghar and Askar were arrested during the Anfal operations against the Kurdish towns during the eighties, she didn't know their fate until the end of the Ba'ath party's regime when it turned out they had been killed and buried in a mass gravesite, till today she still suffers from psychological after-effects of those frightening years. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al Sulaymaniyah on 12/3/2008."
  - Mohdy Ghareeb Sabber, 2007 December 19; 8.08 minutes
    "Born in the city of Al-Qassem in Al-Halla. A teacher from a rural family, he was arrested several times during the seventies, charged with practicing political activities in school. During those arrests, he was severely tortured and degraded. He was arrested again in 1979 and kept at the Security station of Baghdad, charged with belonging to a banned cultural organization. He was tortured in jail and witnessed the torment of women as they were being beaten and electrocuted. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Qassem on 19/12/2007."
  - Ismael Khaul Ibrahim, 2008 March 14; 8.59 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "From the city of Karkuk, he was arrested several times because of his religious inclinations. His first arrest was when he was in junior high school... During the arrests, he was severely tortured and on the final arrest he was referred to the Revolution Court where he was sentenced to 15 years in jail although he was less than 18 years in age then. He was transferred to Abu Ghraib Prison where he stayed for 10 years and was later released with a pardon. This testimony was recorded in the city of Karkuk on 14/3/2008."
  - Abd El Hassan Aydan Douaibel Al Khafaji, 2007 December 12; 9.03 minutes
    "Born in 1962, in the city of Kufa, a clerk from a modest family. Between 1979 and 1982 his young son Mohammad Ali was arrested several times, and he had no affiliations to any political party. His whereabouts were unknown until the year 1991 when his file was located in the Najaf security station and it turned out he was executed in 1982 having been charged with being a member of the Da'wah Party. This testimony was recorded in the city of Kufa on 12/12/2007."
  - Main Hadi Ja Fatta El-Hassona, 2007 September 27; 11.10 minutes
    "From Basrah, he was arrested in 1981 when he was a theology student. He was 15 years old. He was charged with belonging to a cultural-religious organization. After a year of severe torture he was referred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to life imprisonment (for boys) which is 15 years, of which he spent 10 years in Abu Ghraib. This testimony was recorded in the district of Zabeer on 27/9/2007."
  - Zuhair Muslem Hussein Hamadi, 2007 December 17; 8.40 minutes
    "From a modest family in Najaf, during his college years he wrote in a journal for the Islamic movement in the University of Mosel. All who were involved in the publishing of that journal were arrested. He fled and went undercover, and after two years of hiding, he was arrested and placed in the security station of Najaf, then he was transported to the 5th brigade in Baghdad. He was tortured beaten and burned using an electric iron. He started to hallucinate from the severity of the pain. He witnessed the death of a number of detainees from torture. In 1983 he was referred to the Revolution Court where he was sentenced to life imprisonment. This testimony was recorded in the city of Najaf on 17/12/2007."
  - Hanan Hasan Saidradi, 2007 December 17; 9.28 minutes
    From Al-Najaf, she has been interested in the religion since she was at school, so she was subject to harassment and persecution till she ended up in prison with the charge of giving lectures to her fellow colleagues. She was humiliated and tortured by beating, hanging and dragging. Because of the excessive torture and humiliation she thought of committing suicide inside prison. And she remained even after her release under house arrest. This testimony was recorded in Najaf on 17-12-2007."
  - Nasif Jassem Moussa, 2007 February 7; 9.23 minutes
    "From Baghdad, an actor, he was relentlessly harassed during his studies because of his artistic ideas. He was expelled from the Fine Arts Academy because of his critical plays. During the Iraqi-Iranian war he deserted the army then gave himself in when a pardon was issued, but he was arrested and tortured then submitted to the Revolution Court, where he was sentenced to life in prison. This testimony was recorded in Baghdad on 7-2-2007."
  - Amer Hadi Al-Muhaysin, 2007 December 20; 7.16 minutes
    "Born in Al-Hilah in 1950, a teacher, he refused to join the Ba'th party so he was harassed. His brother Kamal was arrested in 1981 and they didn't know anything about him. After 2003, his remains were found in a mass grave. Amer was arrested in 1981, he was independent. He was fiercely tortured and didn't know what his charge was. They kept on moving him from one prison to another for a year. Later he was offered a bargain: he works as an informant for the security services or loses his job. This testimony was recorded in Al-Qasim city on 20-12-2007."
  - Habibah Ahmad Abdallah, 2008 March 13; 10.22 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "From the town of Lazah near Qadir Karm in the district of Karkuk as all the Kurdish cities, her town was subjected continuously and randomly to raids, arrests and killing. During Al-Anfal operations in 1988 her husband, brother and many of her relatives, about 45 of them were arrested, tortured and killed. She witnessed the destruction and burning of houses and the displacement of people. This testimony was recorded in Al-Sulaymaniah on 13-03-2008."
  - Gazi Mazbub Sajit Al-Dami, 2007 December 12; 8.15 minutes
    "Born in Al-Najaf in 1936 he lives in Al-Samawa. His son Ahmad fled after the 1991 uprising to Saudi Arabia, one year later he returned and rejoined his unit where he was arrested and executed. Gazi was arrested for hiding his son and despite his old age he was fiercely tortured. After he was handed the body of his son he was forbidden to hold a funeral for him, and he was arrested again because of that. This testimony was recorded in Al-Samawa on 12-12-2007."
  - Bahaa Eddin Nuri Ahmad, 2008 March 3; 10.12 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in 1956, a teacher from Halabja living in Al-Sulaymaniah Sarkaris neighborhood. 14 members of his family were massacred by chemical weapons in Halabja. In one day, he lost his father, mother, two of his brothers and five of his sisters in addition to his sister's husband and their four children who were all at that same day and place in Halabja. This testimony was recorded in Al-Sulaymaniah on 03-03-2008."
  - Naqi Khalil Salman, 2008 March 16; 9.34 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "From Karkuk his brother was arrested in 1980 after a large arrests campaign in their region called Taza. Muhammad was not a member of any political organization, but was accused of being a member of an Islamic organization and sentenced to death. After his brother's execution, Naqi was severely harassed and persecuted by the security officers and he was attacked in his life and work. This testimony was recorded in Karkuk on 16-03-2008."
  - Kazim Tuhmi Ghazi, 2008 May 5; 7.05 minutes
    "From Al-Samawa... in 1980, two of his brothers Adnan and Nabil were arrested with the charge of participating in a demonstration against the regime. His brother Nabil was sentenced to life and after his release he died in mysterious conditions. As for Adnan, even though he was arrested for only four days he was fiercely tortured and was permanently physically affected. Kazim was arrested many times for unspecified charges and was tortured. This testimony was recorded in Al-Samawa on 05-05-2008."
  - Hussein Hadi Abd-El-Rida Al-Jaburi, 2008 February 8; 13.44 minutes
    "From a big family in Baghdad Al-Kari'at, accused of religious teaching he was arrested in 1991 while a student in the preparatory school and was accused of belonging to Al-Da'wah Party. He was tortured in several detention camps and was placed in solitary confinement where in some cells he slept on blood and hair. He witnessed the death of a prisoner under torture with an electric shock, two years after his arrest he was submitted to court and was sentenced to life imprisonment; he served his sentence in Abu Ghraib. This testimony was recorded in Baghdad on 08-02-2008."
  - Hasan Ali Katafa, 2008 May 9; 9.17 minutes